Guide to the Communist Party of the United States of America Oral History Collection OH.065
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Communist Party of the United States of America Oral History Collection
Bulk, 1980-1990
1962 - 1992
OH.065
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.0 linear feet (1 box; 41 Interviews on 94 cassettes)
The Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), founded in 1919 by members of the left wing of the Socialist Party USA, played an important role in the labor movement, particularly in the building of the Congress of Industrial Organizations, in struggles for civil rights for African Americans, while its cultural initiatives attracted a number of prominent artists and intellectuals, and its struggles to attain and maintain its legality were an important chapter in the history of U.S. civil liberties. The collection contains interviews with 41 Communist Party leaders and activists, including several founding members. The bulk of the interviews were conducted during the 1980s by Mary Licht, then chair of the Party's History Commission. Interviews with African American and Jewish Party members comprise the majority of the collection.
Communist Party of the United States of America. History Commission.
Licht, Mary
Cassette 1-94
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains interviews with 41 Communist Party leaders and activists, including several founding members. The bulk of the interviews were conducted during the 1980s by Mary Licht, then chair of the Party's History Commission. Notable interviewees include: John Abt (an attorney who represented the Party), B.D. Amis, founder of the League of Struggle for Negro Rights, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, feminist and a founder of the American Civil Liberties Union, Hungarian-American artist Hugo Gellert, Simon W. (Si) Gerson, long the Party's leading political campaign manager, Gil Green, Party youth leader in the 1930s, one-time head of the New York State Party organization, and in the 1980s the unofficial leader of the Party's reform "Gorbachevite" wing, Hosea Hudson, leading African American rank and file activist in the South, African American Communist Louise Thompson Patterson, a notable figure during the Harlem Renaissance, and friend of Langston Hughes, Party journalist and newspaper editor John Pittman, and African American Party National Chair Henry Winston.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), founded in 1919 by members of the left wing of the Socialist Party USA, played an important role in the labor movement, particularly in the building of the Congress of Industrial Organizations in the 1930s-1940s, in struggles for civil rights for African Americans, while its cultural initiatives attracted a number of prominent artists and intellectuals, and its struggles to attain and maintain its legality were an important chapter in the history of U.S. civil liberties. Its membership peaked during World War II, reaching some 80,000, organized and led various more broadly based organizations such as the Civil Rights Congress and the International Workers Order, and Communist-led labor unions had a membership of over one million. Its large Jewish membership, and its militant advocacy of civil rights for African Americans are reflected in the backgrounds of the majority of the interviewees.
Access Restrictions
There are currently no user copies of these audiocassettes. Researchers may request the creation of a user copy of one or several individual interviews (requests will take approximately one week to process), to be listened to at the Library. At this time, researchers may cite the interviews, but not quote them.
Abt, John J.; Amis, B. D., b. 1896; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985.; Green, Gil, 1906-; McAdory, Mildred; Moroze, Lewis M.; Patterson, Louise Thompson, 1901-1999; Pittman, John; West, James, 1914-2005; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986.; African American communists |v Interviews.; Communism |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Communists |z United States |v Interviews.; Jewish communists |z United States |v Interviews.; Oral histories (document genres); Women communists |z United States |v Interviews.
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, [Feb 1983] (Box 1, Cassette 1)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, [Feb 1983] (Box 1, Cassette 2)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, [Feb 1983] (Box 1, Cassette 3)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 4, Feb 28, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 4)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 5, Feb 28, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 5)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 6, Feb 28, 1983; Mar 3, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 6)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 7, Mar 3, 1983; Mar 10, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 7)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 8, Mar 10, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 8)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 9, Mar 10, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 9)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 10, Mar 10, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 10)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 11, Mar 17, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 11)
- Abt, John. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 12, Apr 27, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 12)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Tape 1, Nov 16, 1988 (Box 1, Cassette 13)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Tape 2, Nov 16, 1988 (Box 1, Cassette 14)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Interviewed by Miriam Crawford. Tape 1, Feb 1, 1989 (Box 1, Cassette 15)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Interviewed by Miriam Crawford. Tape 2, Feb 1, 1989 (Box 1, Cassette 16)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Tape 1, Jul 24 (Box 1, Cassette 17)
- Amis, Benjamin DeWayne (B. D.). Tape 3, Jul 24 (Box 1, Cassette 18)
- Bart, Phil. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Sep 26, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 19)
- Bart, Phil. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Sep 26, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 20)
- Carroll, Esther. Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 21)
- Cooke, Marvel. Interviewed by Mary Licht, Aug 16, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 21A)
- Dolson, James [Copy 1], undated (Box 1, Cassette 22)
- Dolson, James [Copy 2], undated (Box 1, Cassette 23)
- Du Bois, William E. Burghardt [User copy available], undated (Box 1, Cassette 23A)
- Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, Dec 1962 (Box 1, Cassette 24)
- Freedman, David M. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 25)
- Freedman, David M. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, undated (Box 1, Cassette 26)
- Gaulden, Leila (Rose). Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 27)
- Gellert, Hugo. Interviewed by Mary Licht, Mar 11, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 28)
- Gerson, Simon W. (Si). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Feb 24, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 29)
- Gerson, Simon W. (Si). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Mar 3, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 30)
- Gerson, Simon W. (Si). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, Mar 3, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 31)
- Green, Gil. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Oct 3, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 32)
- Green, Gil. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Oct 3, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 33)
- Green, Gil. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, Oct 20, 1983; Nov 2, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 34)
- Henderson, Joseph. Interviewed by Margaret Baldridge. Tape 1, Sep 23, 1992 (Box 1, Cassette 35)
- Henderson, Joesph. Interviewed by Margaret Baldridge. Tape 2, Sep 30, 1992 (Box 1, Cassette 36)
- Hudson, Hosea. Tape 3, Mar 22 (Box 1, Cassette 37)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 38)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 2, undated (Box 1, Cassette 39)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 40)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 4, undated (Box 1, Cassette 41)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 5, undated (Box 1, Cassette 42)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 6, undated (Box 1, Cassette 43)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 7, undated (Box 1, Cassette 44)
- Huff, Henry. Tape 8, undated (Box 1, Cassette 45)
- Komorowski, Conrad. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 46)
- Komorowski, Conrad. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, undated (Box 1, Cassette 47)
- Komorowski, Conrad. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 48)
- Lumer, Bob (Speaking about the life of his father, Hy Lumer). Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 49)
- Lustig, James. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 50)
- Maurin, Ed. Interviewed by Ann Timpson (Boston, MA) [Copy 1], Apr 19, 1975 (Box 1, Cassette 51)
- Maurin, Ed. Interviewed by Ann Timpson (Boston, MA) [Copy 2], Apr 19, 1975 (Box 1, Cassette 52)
- McAdory, Mildred (Known as Mildred Edelman). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 53)
- McAdory, Mildred (Known as Mildred Edelman). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, undated (Box 1, Cassette 54)
- McAdory, Mildred (Known as Mildred Edelman). Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 55)
- Moroze, Lewis. Interviewed by Mary Licht, Apr 10, 1986 (Box 1, Cassette 56)
- N., Joe. Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 57)
- Nicholas, Elizabeth. Interviewed by Mary Licht (Mountain View, CA), Nov 11, 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 58)
- Neuberger, Samuel. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Dec 16, 1982 (Box 1, Cassette 59)
- Neuberger, Samuel. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Dec 16, 1982 (Box 1, Cassette 60)
- Neuberger, Samuel. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, Dec 16, 1982 (Box 1, Cassette 61)
- Neuberger, Samuel. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 4, Dec 16, 1982 (Box 1, Cassette 62)
- Patterson, Louise Thompson. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 63)
- Patterson, Louise Thompson. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 64)
- Patterson, Louise Thompson. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 4, undated (Box 1, Cassette 65)
- Pittman, John. Interview by Mary Licht [Copy 1], undated (Box 1, Cassette 66)
- Pittman, John. Interview by Mary Licht [Copy 2], undated (Box 1, Cassette 67)
- Rigerman, Paula C., Apr 10, 1981 (Box 1, Cassette 68)
- Riskin, Ben. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Mar 8, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 69)
- Riskin, Ben. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Mar 8, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 70)
- Rosen, Abe. (New Brunswick, NJ), May 14, 1975 (Box 1, Cassette 71)
- Rosen, Pauline. Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 72)
- Rubell, David. Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 73)
- Seltzer, David (Known as Donald Spring). Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 74)
- Seltzer, Edka. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 75)
- Seltzer, Edka. Interviewed by Mary Licht and Carrol [?] (Queens, NY). Tape 2, Feb 5, 1985 (Box 1, Cassette 76)
- Simkin, Jerry. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, undated (Box 1, Cassette 77)
- Simkin, Jerry. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, undated (Box 1, Cassette 78)
- Simkin, Jerry. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 3, undated (Box 1, Cassette 79)
- Simkin, Jerry. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 4, undated (Box 1, Cassette 80)
- Stevens, Donald. (Minneapolis, MN). Tape 1, May 19, 1973 (Box 1, Cassette 81)
- Stevens, Donald. (Minneapolis, MN). Tape 2, May 19, 1973 (Box 1, Cassette 82)
- Stevens, Donald. (Minneapolis, MN). Tape 3, May 19, 1973 (Box 1, Cassette 83)
- Sykes, Frank. Interviewed by Martin Halpern (Detroit, MI). Tape 1, Feb 15, 1981 (Box 1, Cassette 84)
- Sykes, Frank. Interviewed by Martin Halpern (Detroit, MI). Tape 2, Feb 15, 1981 (Box 1, Cassette 85)
- Sykes, Frank. Interviewed by Martin Halpern (Detroit, MI). Tape 3, Feb 15, 1981 (Box 1, Cassette 86)
- Tolopko, Leon. Interviewed by Mary Licht, undated (Box 1, Cassette 87)
- West, Jim. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Mar 12, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 88)
- West, Jim. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Mar 26, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 89)
- Willis, Agnes (Wendy). Interviewed by Mary Licht, May 30, 1984 (Box 1, Cassette 90)
- Wilson, Charles. Interviewed by May Licht, Nov 1983 (Box 1, Cassette 91)
- Winston, Fern. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 1, Sep 14, 1992 (Box 1, Cassette 92)
- Winston, Fern. Interviewed by Mary Licht. Tape 2, Sep 14, 1992 (Box 1, Cassette 93)
- Winter, Karl. Interviewed by Mary Licht, Aug 6, 1990 (Box 1, Cassette 94)